I hope not to offend
with my demonstration
the protocol of this House.
But I believe that
you cannot remain
omissive,
you will not be able to remain
oblivious
to this aggression,
moved by economic power,
by greed,
by ignorance of what it means to be indigenous.
Indigenous people
have a way of thinking,
have a way of living,
have fundamental conditions for their existence,
and for the manifestation of their tradition,
of their life, of their culture
that do not endanger, and have never endangered
the existence of the animals that live around indigenous areas
let alone other human beings.
I believe that none of you can ever point to
acts, attitudes of the indigenous people of Brazil
that have put at risk either the life
or the property of any person,
of any human group in this country.
And today we are the target of an aggression
that intends to strike
in essence
our faith,
our confidence that dignity still exists,
that it is still possible to build a society
that knows how to respect the weakest;
that knows how to respect those
who do not have the money to maintain a campaign
of incessant defamation.
That knows how to respect
the people who have always lived
in the absence of all wealth.
People who live in houses covered with straw,
who sleep on mats on the ground
must not be identified in any way
as the people who are the enemy of Brazil's interests,
the enemy of the interests of the nation,
and who jeopardise any development.
The indigenous people
have watered with blood every hectare
of Brazil's 8 million square kilometres,
you are witnesses of this.
I'd like to thank
the President of this House,
I thank you all,
and I hope my words have not
offended
the feelings of the gentlemen in this House.
Defense of the Popular Constitutional Amendment dealing with the rights of Indigenous people in Brazil
Plenary of the House of Representatives in Brasília
September 4, 1987
Thank you.